Ralph Deterling Papers MS220
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Ralph Deterling Papers
1959 -- 1974
1959 -- 1990
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Deterling, Ralph
MS220
3.6 Linear Feet
Arrangement
This collection is organized into 4 series: Legacy collection documentation folder; Committee meeting minutes; Correspondence; and Subject files.
Custodial History
This collection was originally part of the archives of the New England Medical Center (NEMC), which closed in 1990. The material was received by the NEMC archives from Dr. Deterling in 1983. The collection was processed by Christine Villani, under the supervision of Dave Nathan, archivist at the NEMC archives in June 1987, and had the following NEMC acquisition number: 83-7.
In spring 2013, NEMC material was transferred from NEMC to a restoration company for conservation treatment, and was then transferred to off-site storage in custody of Digital Collections and Archives (DCA). In December 2014 and January 2015, the material was transferred to DCA for processing. Some material originally in the NEMC archives was not transferred to DCA, due to either poor condition or loss.
Scope and Contents
This collection primarily contains the correspondence of Ralph A. Deterling, Jr., M.D., during his time as both Professor of Surgery at Tufts University School of Medicine and Surgeon-in-Chief at the New England Medical Center Hospitals (NEMCH). Correspondence folders contain letters of recommendation, applications for research endeavors, and patient reports, reflecting Deterling's roles not only as a surgeon and professor, but also as executive administrator.
Also represented in the collection are meeting minutes and reports from various committees on which Deterling served, including the Tufts Medical Center Associates (TMCA) and the NEMCH. These meeting minutes document staff reorganization at TMCA, financial arrangements between New England Center Hospital (NECH) and its professional staff, and the planning of the Tufts-New England Medical Center (T-NEMC).
Articles published in medical journals and speeches given at symposiums, detailing Deterling's research in cardiovascular surgery and implants, are included in the Subject files series. Many items in the collection document Deterling's role in the evolution of the New England Medical Center and its partnership with Tufts University School of Medicine.
Consult the Photographs and audiovisual materials series of the New England Medical Center records (MS099.001) for images of Deterling.
This collection suffered extensive water damage due to a flood before it was in the custody of DCA. It underwent conservation efforts before processing, but several materials, particularly folders, scrapbooks, and bound volumes, are still warped or retain a musty odor.
Related Materials
MS099, New England Medical Center records, DCA
Biographical / Historical
Ralph Alden Deterling, Jr., M.D. was born on April 29, 1917 in Williamsburg Pennsylvania. He received his MD in 1942 from Stanford University and his Doctorate in Surgery in 1947 from the University of Minnesota. Fifteen years later, he would receive an award from his alma mater for his achievements in surgery at the New England Medical Center.
Dr. Deterling's career as a surgeon was concurrent with several teaching appointments, beginning at Columbia University in 1948, where he eventually became an Associate Professor of Surgery. He held surgeon positions at several local hospitals during this time, including Presbyterian Hospital, Manhattan Veteran Hospital, Paterson General Hospital, and United States Naval Hospitals between 1948 and 1959. He played a directorial role at several surgical research laboratories, and became instrumental in developing artificial vascular graphs.
In 1959 Dr. Deterling came to Tufts, where he was named professor and chair of the Department of Surgery. He was also appointed as the Surgeon-in-Chief of the New England Medical Center, positions he assumed until his retirement from medicine in 1974. During his time at Tufts and NEMC, he continued the work of his predecessors, installing full-time faculty at NEMC and other local hospitals, as well as continuing to develop a surgical residency program for the School of Medicine. This surgical program worked in cooperation with the hospitals at NEMC. Dr. Deterling was a member of several committees, including the Tufts Medical Center Associates, which proposed the integration of the clinical departments at the New England Medical Center Hospital and the Tufts University School of Medicine.
Dr. Deterling's research in surgery was as an integral component to his work as a teacher and surgeon at Tufts. His contribution to surgical research is represented in the many societies of which he was a member, if not a leader. In fact, he was involved in the organization of several surgical societies. He served as Secretary-General, and later President of the International Cardiovascular Society. He was also president of the New England Society of Vascular Surgery.
Dr. Deterling died in Lincoln, Massachusetts, in 1992. His son, William, is also a surgeon.
Deterling, Ralph A. Jr., M.D., 1917-1992; Tufts Medical Center; New England Medical Center; Tufts-New England Medical Center; Tufts College. Medical School; Tufts University. School of Medicine; New England Medical Center Hospital; Surgery; Cardiac intensive care; Heart--Surgery; Hospitals--United States--Administration; International Cardiovascular Society; Medical care; Surgeons; University history; Hospitals--Medical staff; Medicine -- History; Medical history
- Legacy collection documentation, 1990; MS220.001; 1.2 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains the finding aids by NEMC archivist Dave Nathan, as well as NEMC acquisition records that detail what was accessioned by the NEMC archives from Ralph Deterling.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Legacy collection documentation folder, 1990; MS220.001.001.00001 (Box MS220 Shared 1)
- Committee meeting minutes, 1967 -- 1976; MS220.002; 1.2 Linear Feet
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged alphabetically.
  - Committee on hospital infections, 1974 -- 1976; MS220.002.001.00002 (Box MS220 Shared 1)
  - Joint planning commission, 1968; MS220.002.001.00003 (Box MS220 Shared 1)
  - Joint staff-trustee liaison committee, 1967 -- 1968; MS220.002.001.00004 (Box MS220 Shared 1)
  - Medical board, 1973 -- 1975; MS220.002.001.00005 (Box MS220 Shared 1)
  - Space committee, 1968 -- 1973; MS220.002.001.00006 (Box MS220 Shared 1)
  - Special committee on staff financial relationships (TMCA), 1972 -- 1975; MS220.002.001.00007 (Box MS220 Shared 1)
- Correspondence, 1959 -- 1982; MS220.003; 2.4 Linear Feet
  - Al-Naaman, Yousif, 1975 -- 1977; MS220.003.001.00008 (Box MS220 Shared 1)
  - Billig, Donal, 1968 -- 1973; MS220.003.001.00009 (Box MS220 Shared 1)
  - Binder, Sheldon, 1972 -- 1978; MS220.003.001.00010 (Box MS220 Shared 1)
  - Birtwell, William, 1965 -- 1973; MS220.003.001.00011 (Box MS220 Shared 1)
  - Callow, Allan, 1970 -- 1976; MS220.003.001.00012 (Box MS220 Shared 1)
  - Chatterjee, Khagendra, 1972 -- 1978; MS220.003.001.00013 (Box MS220 Shared 1)
  - Doku, H. Chris, 1964 -- 1973; MS220.003.001.00014 (Box MS220 Shared 1)
  - Easton, Mahlon, 1965 -- 1969; MS220.003.001.00015 (Box MS220 Shared 1)
  - Egdahl, Richard, 1967 -- 1973; MS220.003.001.00016 (Box MS220 Shared 1)
  - Epstein, Robert, 1969 -- 1974; MS220.003.001.00017 (Box MS220 Shared 1)
  - Everhart, David, 1971 -- 1975; MS220.003.001.00018 (Box MS220 Shared 1)
  - Flint, Paul, 1964 -- 1968; MS220.003.001.00019 (Box MS220 Shared 1)
  - Howalt, Jay, 1969 -- 1973; MS220.003.001.00020 (Box MS220 Shared 1)
  - Hume, Michael, 1967 -- 1978; MS220.003.001.00021 (Box MS220 Shared 1)
  - Kennedy, Colleen, 1978; MS220.003.001.00022 (Box MS220 Shared 1)
  - Lister, Julius, 1964 -- 1978; MS220.003.001.00023 (Box MS220 Shared 1)
  - Mahony, David, 1969 -- 1975; MS220.003.001.00024 (Box MS220 Shared 1)
  - Martyak, Stephen, 1975 -- 1977; MS220.003.001.00025 (Box MS220 Shared 1)
  - McCombs, Peter, 1976 -- 1978; MS220.003.001.00026 (Box MS220 Shared 1)
  - Mitchell, George, 1959 -- 1978; MS220.003.001.00027 (Box MS220 Shared 1)
  - Moran, John, 1967 -- 1972; MS220.003.001.00028 (Box MS220 Shared 1)
  - Park, David, 1977; MS220.003.001.00029 (Box MS220 Shared 1)
  - Quarles, John, 1970; MS220.003.001.00030 (Box MS220 Shared 1)
  - Rallo, Vito, 1971 -- 1975; MS220.003.001.00031 (Box MS220 Shared 1)
  - Rangel, Decio, 1979; MS220.003.001.00032 (Box MS220 Shared 1)
  - Reif, Arnold, 1971 -- 1979; MS220.003.001.00033 (Box MS220 Shared 1)
  - Reynolds, Edwin, 1976 -- 1978; MS220.003.002.00001 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
    Davis and Geck.
  - Rheinlander, Harold, 1971 -- 1976; MS220.003.002.00002 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
  - Schwartz, Bernard, 1967 -- 1979; MS220.003.002.00003 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
  - Schwartz, Robert, 1960 -- 1972; MS220.003.002.00004 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
  - Schwartz, William, 1965 -- 1973; MS220.003.002.00005 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
  - Segal, Maurice, 1966 -- 1980; MS220.003.002.00006 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
  - Selverstone, Bertram, 1959 -- 1969; MS220.003.002.00007 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
  - Sindell, David, 1975; MS220.003.002.00008 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
  - Slater, Robert, 1961 -- 1962; MS220.003.002.00009 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
  - Soroff, Harry, 1967 -- 1978; MS220.003.002.00010 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
  - Stanton, Richard, 1975 -- 1982; MS220.003.002.00011 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
  - Stein, Bennett, 1971 -- 1974; MS220.003.002.00012 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
  - Stojanovic, Vojislav, 1973; MS220.003.002.00013 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
  - Struass, Maurice, 1964 -- 1971; MS220.003.002.00014 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
  - Sugarman, Herman, 1960 -- 1971; MS220.003.002.00015 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
  - Sullivan, John, 1959 -- 1975; MS220.003.002.00016 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
  - Tarasaov, Michael, 1961 -- 1964; MS220.003.002.00017 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
  - Thibodeau, Arthur, 1959 -- 1974; MS220.003.002.00018 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
  - Viguers, Richard, 1968 -- 1969; MS220.003.002.00019 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
  - Weinstein, Louis, 1960 -- 1971; MS220.003.002.00020 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
  - Wulff, Lister, 1961 -- 1976; MS220.003.002.00021 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
  - Gifford, Harry, 1976; MS220.003.002.00022 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
- Subject files, 1959 -- 1981; MS220.004; 2.4 Linear Feet
  - 23rd Congress of the International Society of Surgery, 1969 -- 1979; MS220.004.002.00023 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
  - Advisees (RAD), 1976 -- 1977; MS220.004.002.00024 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
  - American Trauma Society, 1975 -- 1977; MS220.004.002.00025 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
  - Blood Bank, 1977; MS220.004.002.00026 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
  - Board of Directors, Charitable and Education, 1964 -- 1977; MS220.004.002.00027 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
  - Charlton Fund, 1959 -- 1963; MS220.004.002.00028 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
  - Development and evaluation of novel porous polymers for use in cardiovascular prostheses, 1972; MS220.004.002.00029 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
  - Disaster plan, 1976; MS220.004.002.00030 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
  - Equipment, surgery, 1969; MS220.004.002.00031 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
  - Graduate Degree Program, 1975 -- 1976; MS220.004.002.00032 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
  - In-patient analysis, 1973; MS220.004.002.00033 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
  - Industrial Clinic, 1979 -- 1981; MS220.004.002.00034 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
  - Joint committee on accreditation, 1972; MS220.004.002.00035 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
  - Lemuel Shattuck Pulmonary Disease Conference, 1976; MS220.004.002.00036 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
  - Long Island Hospital, 1976 -- 1977; MS220.004.002.00037 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
  - Long term fate of aortic and arterial homografts, 1969; MS220.004.002.00038 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
  - Malden Hospital, 1966; MS220.004.002.00039 (Box MS220 Shared 2)
  - Pan American Hospital, 1975 -- 1976; MS220.004.003.00001 (Box 3)
  - Pan American Medical Association, 1975 -- 1977; MS220.004.003.00002 (Box 3)
  - Pan Pacific Surgical Association, 1975 -- 1978; MS220.004.003.00003 (Box 3)
  - Pharmacy, 1962 -- 1978; MS220.004.003.00004 (Box 3)
  - Position inquiries, 1974 -- 1980; MS220.004.003.00005 (Box 3)
  - Presidential address to the International Cardiovascular Society, 1971; MS220.004.003.00006 (Box 3)
  - Research committee, 1976 -- 1978; MS220.004.003.00007 (Box 3)
  - Shattuck Hospital, 1975 -- 1980; MS220.004.003.00008 (Box 3)
  - Symposium on current trends in vascular surgery, 1976; MS220.004.003.00009 (Box 3)
  - Symposium on trauma and critical care, 1974; MS220.004.003.00010 (Box 3)
  - Use of injected neoprene latex in digest studies, 1974; MS220.004.003.00011 (Box 3)
  - Veterinary Medicine, 1973 -- 1981; MS220.004.003.00012 (Box 3)
  - Winchester Hospital, 1976; MS220.004.003.00013 (Box 3)
  - What has surgery to offer for coronary insufficiency?, 1964; MS220.004.003.00014 (Box 3)